Inventory of the L.L. Newton Papers, 1837-1953 (Bulk 1926-1942)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
L.L. Newton papers
1837-1953
1926-1942
Newton, L.L.
00017
.7 cubic ft. (2 boxes) + oversize folder
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Historical materials collected by a Lander, Wyoming, newspaper editor.
Biography of L.L. Newton
Len L. Newton was a Wyoming newspaperman and historian of the Fremont County area. He was born in Wyanet, Illinois, in 1877 and came to Cody, Wyoming, in 1901 to work as a printer on the Cody Enterprise. Later, in association with his father, he established the Northern Wyoming Herald which eventually consolidated with the Cody Enterprise. In 1924 he sold his interest in the Enterprise and bought the Wyoming State Journal located in Lander, Wyoming. He was appointed by Governor Robert Carey to supervise the first bond issue for the state highway system. Governor Frank Emerson appointed him director of the Wyoming State Department of Commerce and Industry in 1929. Newton sold the Wyoming State Journal to his son, Ernest L. Newton, in 1938. During World War II he worked as editor of the Alliance, Nebraska, Times Herald. Newton took great interest in the early history of Wyoming, particularly the Lander and Fremont County area. He was active in Republican politics and outspoken on controversial questions of his time. L.L. Newton died in Lander at the age of 76 on July 20, 1954.
Scope and Content
The L.L Newton Papers primarily concern the history of Lander and Fremont County in Wyoming. The correspondence and manuscripts focus on early settlers in the area. In addition to narratives and personal reminiscences there are several lists of names of early settlers. The collection also contains correspondence and council minutes from the Shoshone and Arapahoe business councils on the Wind River Reservation.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by L.L. Newton at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from L.L. Newton in 1945.
Access Terms
Frontier and pioneer life -- Wyoming -- Lander; Frontier and pioneer life -- Wyoming -- Fremont County; Wind River Indian Reservation (wyo.); Lander (Wyo.); Fremont County (Wyo.); Wyoming -- History -- To 1889; Wyoming -- History -- 1890-1918; Wyoming -- History -- 1919-1945; Wyoming -- History -- 1946-1999
Pioneers; Social Life and Customs; City and Town Life; Wyoming
Container List
- Series I. Historical Papers
  - Arapahoe and Cheyenne History: Typescripts from unidentified source, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baldwin, Josephine (Mrs. Noyes): Notes on life, by Mrs. Chittim, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blizzard of 1883: Letter and manuscript by Peter Sherlock, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blizzard of 1883: Supplementary notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bowman, Jennie Riley (Mrs. R.E.): Manuscripts relating experiences at Chicago World’s Fairs of 1893, 1896, and 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bright, Alfred: Notes on life (Hoosit no. 45), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brokenhorn (Mrs.): Manuscript by E.J. Farlow, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brown, N.H.: Notes and manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Buffalo Bill: Typescript, “The Fight on the War Bonnet Creek…Killing of Yellow Hand,” by Charles Ackenhausen; notes, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Calamity Jane: Manuscript by Tobe Borner; manuscript by Tacetta Walker, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Calamity Jane: Letters from Jessie Murray, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cheney, E.F.: Manuscript by Emma Cheney Nottage, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Crowheart Butte: “The Indian Legend of Crowheart Butte,” Poem by Addie Holmberg, uundated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dickie, James: Autobiographical letter, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Farlow, E.J.: “The Pioneer or the Life of the Indians,” autobiographical manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fremont County Officers, 1884-1936: Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fremont County Pioneer Association: Manuscript of article, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fremont County Pioneers - Biographical Cards: Matilda Cheney; Mrs. Porter B. Coolidge; William Cook; John George Hallam; Mary Elizabeth Lamb; Porter Lamb; Arminto Mohr; Jennie Black Pitts; Ida Peterson Rogers; John Rogers; Franklin Beattie Sheldon; Isaphenia Sidenbender, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fremont County Pioneers - Letters: From Emmett Connell; Al Heder; W.P. Mills; Hilda Price; H.E. Wadsworth; unsigned; regarding names and experiences of early residents, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fremont County Pioneers - Lists: Names of early residents, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Irwin, Frank: Letter from Robert McAuley, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jackson, George: Notes on interview by Edith Alger, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jackson, “Teton”: Letter from W.L. Simpson, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Johnson, John S.: Manuscript (Hoosit no. 8), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Killed and Wounded at or Near South Pass, 1867-1873: List, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Kinney, Kinch: Letter from L.L. Newton, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Knifong, Clarence J.: Obituary form, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lambertson, Eva G.: Manuscript reminiscences “A Long Trail”; poem; article, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lander Creamery: Typescript article, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Logue, Harry R.: Letter with reminiscences, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - A Lost Mine: Manuscript by Fannie Allen, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lowe, Benjamin F.: Letter and manuscript by Laura Lowe, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - McAuley, Robert: Letters from Robert McAuley, James McGinnis, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - McGraw, William M.: Notes on life, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Morris, Esther: Regarding monument in South Pass City, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Murphy, Mike: Notes on life, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Nalls, Stuart: Notes on life (Hoosit no. 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Nickerson, H.G.: Notes on life, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - O’Grady, Pat: Letter from Peter Sherlock; original report of Maj. J.J. Upham of 5th Cavalry regarding accidental death of soldier Pat O’Grady near Ft. Washakie, 1880, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Padget, John W.: Typescript from printed source (Hoosit no. 81), undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Pierce, Hank: Notes on life of stage driver, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Roberts, John (Rev.): Manuscript by Addie E. Holmberg, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sacajawea: Manuscript by Earl L. Raines, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Schuelke (Dr.): Letter from Elise Schuelke Hansen, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sheehan, Michal: Handwritten obituary, circa 1931 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Short, Leonard: Letter, handwritten obituary, 1933, circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Shoshone Sun Dance: Manuscripts by Lynn St. Clair, L.L. Newton, 1936, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Signor, Guy A.: Notes on life (Hoosit no. 5), undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Telegraph Line: Notes from printed source, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Trip from Lander to Cooke City, 1892: Typescript of unsigned letter, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Trip to Yellowstone Park, 1892: Manuscript, author’s signature illegible, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Tweed, Dave: Letters, notes on life, 1935, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Twogwotee Pass Road: Manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Van Patten, Margaretta: Autobiography, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Walker, Tacetta B.: Letters and manuscript, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Washakie: Manuscript by Rev. John Roberts, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Washakie National Forest: “A Brief History of the Washakie National Forest and the Duties and Some Experiences of a Ranger,” typescript by A.G. Clayton, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Whoozit List: Printed list of names, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Wistrand, Lillian: Letters and manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Wolf, Charles T.: Notes on life by Edith K. Alger (Hoosit no. 1), undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Wright, F.T.: Manuscripts regarding Fremont Clipper (early newspaper), 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Wyoming Governors, 1869-1943: Typescript list, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Wyoming Roundup Districts Schedule: Typed notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Series II. Lander and Fremont County
  - Lander: Brochure published by Lander Chamber of Commerce, circa 1927 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Lander For State Capital: Flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, Lander: Golden Jubilee information, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Senior Class Will: By Emily Bates, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Teachers Directory, Fremont County, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Winning of the West: Lander Pioneer Days program, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Series III. Wind River Reservation
  - Correspondence: Typescript copy of letter from John Collier, Commissioner of Indian Affairs, regarding Indian self-government, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence: Office of Indian Affairs, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence: American Indian Federation, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Council Minutes: Shoshone and Arapahoe Councils, June 10-11, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Council Minutes: Shoshone and Arapahoe Business Councils, July 1, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Council Minutes: Shoshone and Arapahoe Business Councils, August 7, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Council Minutes: Arapahoe General Council and Shoshone and Arapahoe Business Councils, September 6, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Council Minutes: Handwritten, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Legal Cases: Notes and printed material regarding land, 1929-1940 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Notes: List of names, undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Report: Indian Lands in Wyoming, by State Planning Board, typescript copy, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series IV. Wyoming
  - Water: Letter from W.E. Zipfel; typescript articles and reports by Zipfel, C.D. Moir, Stuart Chase, G.E.P. Smith, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Wyoming Worth Knowing: Tourist brochure published by Wyoming State Department of Commerce and Industry, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Fort Washakie: Buildings, “Smiling Charlie,” by Carrigen, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Historical: Buffalo Bill; Buffalo Bill grave site; Esther Morris; Major Jackson’s Company marching through Lander; museum displays, circa 1870-circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lander People: Karine Gard; Edward R. Hopper (Ne-a-he-ga-ya-ah); Rev. Frederick Morris, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wyoming State Training School, Lander: Includes program for unveiling of commemorative tablet, circa 1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Newspaper Clippings
  - Biographical, A-C: Jackson Alvese; Calamity Jane; Butch Cassidy; Lon Claytor; William F. Cody; Sherman Coolidge; George A. Custer, 1934-1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Biographical, D-J: James Dickie; Dudley Hale; Wild Bill Hickok; Grace R. Hebard; Thomas B. Hood; Jesse James; Mr. and Mrs. John Jeffrey, 1894, 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Biographical, K-Z: Jason Lee; Benjamin F. Lowe; Bob McAuley; Joseph Meek; Esther Morris; George Parrott; Mr. and Mrs. Leonard Short; Mr. and Mrs. Ray Short; Tom Vernon; Charles Woodard, 1908-1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fort Bridger, 1873, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fur Trade: Page from The Penny Magazine, London, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Indian Subjects: Battle of Little Bighorn; Fighting Indians on Old Trail (North of Saratoga); Mary Harris; Medicine Wheel; Ring Game; Sacajawea’s Grave (includes transcript); St. Stephen’s Mission; Shoshones; Sun Dance; Yellow Calf, 1932-1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Johnson County War: Account of George B. McClellan, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Peek at the Past: Column from Wyoming State Journal, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pony Express and Telegraph, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Saddles: From Cow Country, WSGA newsletter, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Wyoming Places: Cowboy Duel in Hot Springs County; Dubois; Lost Cabin; Occidental Hotel (Buffalo); Petrified Forest in Sweetwater County; Pioneer Park; Rock Springs Coal; South Pass City; Thermopolis Hot Springs; Washakie National Forest, 1925-1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Wyoming Places - Yellowstone Park/Jackson Hole: From Jackson Hole Courier, April 13, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - From Fort Laramie: Article on page of unidentified New York paper, 1853 (Oversize folder)
  - Great Pacific Railroad: Article on page of Newburyport Daily Herald, December 4, 1846 (Oversize folder)
  - The 101 Ranch: Article in Winners of the West, November 1937 (Oversize folder)